Bread and Puppet Theater Collection
© 2005 University of Connecticut
Bread and Puppet Theater Collection.
undated, 1967-1988.
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center.
Bread and Puppet Theater.
.5 linear feet.
MSS19970031
The Bread and Puppet Theater was an experiment political theater troupe founded in 1963 in New York City by Peter Schumann. Performances combined dance, sculpture and large-scale puppets and masks. The performances frequently focused on political and social issues including demonstrations against the U.S. war in Vietnam and injustice in Central America.
History
The Bread and Puppet Theater was an experiment political theater troupe founded in 1963 in New York City by Peter Schumann. Performances combined dance, sculpture and large-scale puppets and masks. The performances frequently focused on political and social issues including demonstrations against the U.S. war in Vietnam and injustice in Central America. In 1970, the troupe moved to Vermont where it was the theater-in-residence at Goddard College in Plainfield, VT. In 1974, the troupe moved to Glover, Vermont. The troupe received numerous awards for its work including the Erasmus Prize of Amsterdam, Obie, President's Award of the Puppeteers of America and Governor's Award of Vermont.
Scope and Content
The collection includes illustrated story scripts, handbills and performance programs, illustrated calendars and other related ephemera and publications.
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of literary and alternative press materials. See also, additional publications of the Bread and Puppet Theater are listed in the Library's online catalog. Materials pertaining to the University's Puppetry Program can be found in the Frank Ballard Papers. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Bibliography
Stefan Brecht. Peter Schumann's Bread and Puppet Theatre, London: Routledge, 1988.
Index Terms
This record series is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Organizations:
Bread and Puppet Theater.
Subjects:
Puppet plays.; Puppets—New York (N.Y.)
Document Types:
Publications.
Restrictions on Access
There are no access restrictions on this collection.
Acquisition Information
Provenance is unknown.
Detailed Description
- Series I: Collection, undated, 1967-1988
  - Illustrated Performance Scripts and Other Storybooks
    - La Ballata Dei XIV; Giorni di Masaniello, 1977 (Box 1:, Folder 1)
    - Othello, 1978 (Box 1:, Folder 2)
    - St. Francis Preaches to the Birds, 1978 [1982] (Box 1:, Folder 3)
    - Washerwoman Nativity, 1979 (Box 1:, Folder 4)
    - Ah! Or The First Washerwoman Cantata, 1980 (Box 1:, Folder 5)
    - This is, 1980 (Box 1:, Folder 6)
    - La Necessite, [1980] (Box 1:, Folder 7)
    - The Rise of the Washerwoman Grace of New York City, 1981/1982 (Box 1:, Folder 8)
    - The Sumpul River Massacre, 1981 (Box 1:, Folder 9)
    - Diagonal Man, 1982 (Box 1:, Folder 10)
    - L'Homme Diagonal, 1982 (Box 1:, Folder 11)
    - The Story of One Who Set Out to Study Fear, 1982-1983 (Box 1:, Folder 12)
    - Insurrection Opera No. 1: The End Falls Before the Beginning, 1983 (Box 1:, Folder 13)
    - Hallelujah, 1983 (Box 1:, Folder 14)
    - Bread, 1984 (Box 1:, Folder 15)
    - Donkey Ride over Dexter Hill, 1984 (Box 1:, Folder 16)
    - Josephine the Singer, ca. 1984 (Box 1:, Folder 17)
    - The Nativity, Crucifixion and Resurrection of Oscar Romero of El Salvador, 1984 (Box 1:, Folder 18)
    - Snow-Bakery, 1984 (Box 1:, Folder 19)
    - Fisherman's Return, undated (Box 1:, Folder 20)
    - A Simple Farmer's Day, undated (Box 1:, Folder 21)
  - Publications
    - Handbills—includes “Short History of Bread and Puppet Theater” (Box 1:, Folder 22)
    - Bread and Puppet Newspapers, 1967-1970 (Box 1:, Folder 23-24)
    - Illustrated Calendars, 1985, 1988 (Box 1:, Folder 25)
    - Bread and Puppet Museum Publications, undated (Box 1:, Folder 26)